<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breefe catechisme so necessary and easie to be learned euen of the simple sort that whosoeuer can not or vvill not attaine to the same, is not to be counted a good Christian, much lesse to be admitted to the Supper of the Lorde. It standeth of three partes. 1. The first sheweth how miserable all men are of them selues. 2. The second, how happy they are that rightly beleeue in Christe. 3. The third, what duetyes they owe vnto God for his great mercy towards them in Christ Iesus.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855840</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855840</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21345</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18158)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21345)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1542:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breefe catechisme so necessary and easie to be learned euen of the simple sort that whosoeuer can not or vvill not attaine to the same, is not to be counted a good Christian, much lesse to be admitted to the Supper of the Lorde. It standeth of three partes. 1. The first sheweth how miserable all men are of them selues. 2. The second, how happy they are that rightly beleeue in Christe. 3. The third, what duetyes they owe vnto God for his great mercy towards them in Christ Iesus.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Hugh Singleton, dwelling in Creede lane, at the signe of the gylden Tunne, and are there to be sold,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another edition of STC 4798.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21345:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21345:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A breefe Catechiſme ſo neceſſary and eaſie to be learned e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the ſimple ſort, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer can not, or vvill not attaine to the ſame, is not to be counted a good Chriſtian, much leſſe to be admitted to the Supper of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It ſtandeth of three parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The firſt ſheweth how miſerable all men are of them ſelues.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The ſecond, how happy they are that rightly beléeue in Chriſte.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>The third, what duetyes they owe vnto God for his great mercy towards them in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by <hi>Hugh Singleton,</hi> dwelling in Creede lane, at the ſigne of the gylden Tunne, and are there to be ſold. 1582.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:21345:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Peter. 3.15.16.</bibl>
                  <p>Sanctifye the Lord God in your harts, and be ready always to giue an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to euery man that aſketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you.</p>
                  <p>And that with méekeneſſe and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, hauing a good conſcience, that when they ſpeake euill of you as of euil doers, they may be aſhamed which blame your good conuerſation in Chriſte.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21345:2"/>
               <head>The firſt parte.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rt not thou a ſeruaunt vnto the almighty God, and Lord of heauen and earth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> I acknowledge myſelfe for euer to be his ſeruaunt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 24.15.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Hath God giuen forth any Lawes, whereby ſeruaunts, should be wel ruled &amp; gouerned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> The holy Scriptures are Gods lawes, wherin he declareth his will &amp; pleaſure,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebru.</hi> 11.2 <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.26 31. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.13</note> the generall ſome and effect whereof is bréefely ſet foorthe vnto vs in the tenne Commaundements.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Rehearſe the tenne Commaundements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label>
                  <list>
                     <head>The firſt Table.</head>
                     <item>i. God ſpake all theſe words and ſaid, I am the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>20.3.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </item>
                     <item>ii Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, nor the likeneſſe of anye thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waters vnder the earth, thou ſhalt not bow down to them
<pb facs="tcp:21345:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>nor woorſhip them, for I the Lord am a ielous God, and viſite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vpon the children, vnto the third &amp; fourth generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hate me, and ſhew mercy vnto thouſand in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue me, and kéepe my commaundements.</item>
                     <item>iii. Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vayne, for the Lorde wyll not holde him guiltles, that taketh his name in vaine.</item>
                     <item>iiii. Remember that thou kéepe holye the Sabboth daye, ſixe dayes ſhalt thou labour and doe all that thou haſt to doo: but the ſeuenth day is the Saboth of the Lord thy God, in it thou ſhalt do no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of work, thou nor thy ſon, thy daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, thy man ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor thy maide ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, thy catel nor the ſtraunger that is within thy gates: for in ſixe dayes the Lorde made Heauen and Earth, the ſea and all that in them is, and reſted the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day, wherefore the Lorde bleſſed the ſeuenth day, and hollowed it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The ſecond Table.</head>
                     <item>v. Honour thy father and thy mother, that thy dayes may be long in the lande which the Lord thy God giueth thée.</item>
                     <item>vi. Thou ſhalt doo no murder.</item>
                     <item>vii. Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie.</item>
                     <item>viii. Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:21345:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <item>ix. Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</item>
                     <item>x. Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbors houſe, thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors wife, nor his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor his Oxe, nor his Aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Art thou able to keepe all theſe lavves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> Euery man is guiltye of the breache héereof, not onely in reſpect of theyr ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall or birthe ſinne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.22 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.8</note> but alſo otherwiſe in thought woord and déede.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>What is the daunger of breaking anye of theſe lavves of almightie God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> The iuſt puniſhment of breaking any of God his laws,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>mat.</hi> 5.19.22 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.10.</note> yea if it were but once in all my life, it is loſſe of Gods fauour, the purchaſing of his heauy diſpleaſure which bringeth euerlaſting death, bothe of ſoule and body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>¶ The ſecond part.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Hovv shall you eſcape this great daunger, and feareful punishment of your ſinnes. Wil not your good deedes ſerue to make ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds
<pb facs="tcp:21345:4"/>&amp; ſo deliuer you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this punishment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> My good déeds wil not helpe to ſaue me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this puniſhment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſſ.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Actes.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.21.</note> nor any thing els, but only Ieſus Chriſt hath deliuerd me.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>How hath Ieſus Chriſt ſaued and deliuered you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this great punishment of your ſins?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> Ieſus Chriſt hath deliuered me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhement of my ſin,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10 <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.13 <hi>Eſai.</hi> 53.5. <hi>Lol.</hi> 1.19.20 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16.18 <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.20.</note> becauſe he being both God and man, hath ſuffered all the puniſhment which my ſins deſerued, &amp; hath fulfiled the lawe of God perfectly for me, and thereby hath reſtored me for euer to the loue and fauour of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Are all then ſaued by this ſuffering and death of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> Only they are ſaued by Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.28.</note> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath done all thinges touching ſaluation, not only for other but alſo eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for them ſelues, the effect of which faith is contained in the Creede.<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <note n="2b." place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21 <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24.25.</note>
                  <hi>Reherſe the Creede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> 
                  <hi>I</hi> Beleeue<note n="1.a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.45</note> in God the Father almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty<note n="c." place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4.27. <hi>Heh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.38.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21345:4"/>maker of heauen and earth. And in <hi>2.b</hi> Ieſus <hi>c</hi> Chriſt his<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Io.</hi> 1.14.18.</note> onely ſon our<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ma.</hi> 28.18. 1. <hi>Pe.</hi> 1.18.19.</note> Lord. Which was conceiued<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>mat.</hi> 1.8.20.</note> by the holy ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Mary. Suffered<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.24.33.46.</note> vnder Ponce Pilate,<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.46. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.37 <hi>Lu.</hi> 22.44.</note> was crucified, dead and buried,<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.8 9. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.4 12.</note> he diſcended into hell the third daye hee roſe againe from the dead. He<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 1.9.</note> aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 7.55.56. <hi>Lol.</hi> 3.1.</note> ſitteth at the righte hande of God the father Almighty. From thence<note n="m" place="margin">2. <hi>Lor.</hi> 3.10.</note> ſhall he come to iudge both the quick and the dead. I beleeue in<note n="3.n" place="margin">
                     <hi>mat.</hi> 28.19 <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3, 4. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.</note> the holy ghoſt. The<note n="4.o" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. 1. <hi>Lor.</hi> 14.33 <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18 19.</note> holy Catholicke church. The communion<note n="p" place="margin">1. <hi>Lor.</hi> 12.12.</note> of Saints. The<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 3.24.25.</note> forgiuenes of ſinnes. The<note n="r" place="margin">1. <hi>Lor.</hi> 15.53.45. <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.25.26.</note> reſurrection of the body. And the <hi>s</hi> lyfe euerlaſtyng Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>By vvhat meanes haue vvee ſuch a true faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> It is the gift of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Hovv dooth God vvorke this faith in vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> By the preaching of the word of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Is this faithfullie framed and made ſtronge in vs at the first, or in one houre?</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">2. <hi>Lor.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.23.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21345:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> Fayth is increaſed by little and little,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.17 <hi>Gala.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11 12.13. 1. <hi>Theſſa.</hi> 5.19.20.</note> and made ſtronge in vs by the dilligent hearing of the woord of God, and by the vſe of his ſacraments.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Hovv many Sacraments be there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> There be two Sacraments,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. 1. <hi>Co.</hi> 10.2.3 <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25 <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19 <hi>Mat</hi> 26.2.6 <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.26.</note> Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>What benefite haue you by Baptiſme, and to vvhat end ſerueth it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> By Baptiſme the holy Ghoſt aſſureth me that as my body is ſprinckled with water,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 22.16.</note> ſo my ſoule,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21</note> by the bloudſhedding of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Colo.</hi> 2.12.</note> is ſprinckled and waſhed from all the guilt and puniſhment of my ſin, and alſo héerby I profeſſe my ſelfe to die with Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</note> as concerning ſinne, &amp; liue in him as concerning righteouſnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>To vvhat end ſerueth the ſupper of the lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> In the ſupper of the Lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19.22.24. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 10.16 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23</note> I am by the ſpirit of God aſſured, that as the breade broken, and the wine powred out be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto me, euen ſo was the bodye
<pb facs="tcp:21345:5"/>of Chriſte broken, &amp; his bloud ſhed, as a full recompence to God for my ſinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>¶ The third part.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>For aſmuch then as God of his infinite loue, hath giuen his ovvne ſonne to raunſome vs from the power of ſinne, death &amp; hel, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce vs to the honour of his children, &amp; heyres of his kingdome: ſeeing it pleaſeth him to giue vs faith, and daily to nourish &amp; encreaſe it in vs more and more, by his word and ſacraments: by the which faith we lay hold vpon Chriſt, and make him with al his merites and treaſures our ovvne: ſo that novv not onely all our ſinnes are remooued from vs, but alſo his righteouſnes, holines, &amp; perfection, is accounted ours before God: Do you not thinke that vve are very deepely bound vnto him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> Yes verely, I am ſo much bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to god,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al my life ought to be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to his Maieſty, for his great mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Is then this doctrine vvhich shevveth vs that vve are ſaued by Ieſus Chriſte onely, and not by our ovvne vvorkes, any occaſion of vvicked life, as the Papistes ſlaunder it?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21345:6"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> This doctrin is no occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wicked life but the greateſt reſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to perſwade me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be diligent and zealous in good workes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 24.14.18. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 130.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.1 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Titus.</hi> 2.11.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>Are there no other good deedes required of christia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but giuing almes, viſiting the ſick, building of ſcholes, &amp; houſes for the poore? An,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.2. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3.</note> As theſe are good déeds, &amp; ſuch as highly pleaſe God, being don in ſuch maner as the word of God doth teach vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, with a true faith in Chriſt &amp; pure loue toward our Brethren,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 20.3.4 <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.36.</note> So are there many other much more excellent then theſe, as the pure worſhipping of God both with ſoule and body:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 13.36</note> truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; depending of his good prouidence both in proſperity &amp; aduerſity:<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 10.42.</note> hering of his holy word:<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Cloſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Iacob.</hi> 5.20.</note> exhortations and admonitions one to another, eſpecially to ſuch as we haue ſpeciall charge ouer:<note n="f" place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.14 15.</note> prayſing God for all his mercies and continuall benefits poured vpon vs: and laſte of all,<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 20 <hi>Epheſſ.</hi> 6 10</note> faithfull prayers for all ſuch things as we ſtand in néede of.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label> 
                  <hi>To vvhom ought we to make our praiers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>An.</label> We muſt pray to our louing and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God alone,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15 <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.24.</note> and to none but him.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21345:6"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Qu.</label> 
                  <hi>VVhat thinges ought vve to praie for?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> We muſt pray, not onely for all things néedfull for our ſelues and the Churche of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.29. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18.19</note> but eſpecially for thoſe thinges which appertaine to the ſetting foorth of the glory of God, euen as we are taught in the Lords prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Qu.</label> 
                  <hi>Rehearſe the Lords praier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> OVr Father which art in heauen, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy name.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 6.9.</note> Thy kingdome come. Thy will be don in earth, as it is in Heauen. Giue vs this day our dayly bread. And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs. And lead vs not into temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But deliuer vs from euill. For thine is the kingdome the power and the glory, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Qu.</label> 
                  <hi>Hovv may we be aſſured that God wil heare vs, ſeeing vve are ſinners?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Aunſwer.</label> Becauſe we offer vp our praiers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.23 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.1 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> not in our owne name, nor in the name of any creature, but of the ſonne of God our Sauiour, who is alwayes in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, to entreate his Maieſtie for vs, his poore ſeruaunts.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:21345:7"/>
            <head>Certaine neceſſarie inſtructions meete to be taught the younger ſort, before they come to be partakers of the holy Communion.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> 
               <hi>What doo you come to receiue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>An.</label> I come to receiue the Lords ſupper.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> 
               <hi>What is the Lordes Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>An.</label> The Lords ſupper is a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to ſhew forth in moſt liuely and euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t manner, his painfull ſuffering of death for vs, by the outward ſignes of bread and wine.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> 
               <hi>Wherefore comeſt thou to receiue the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>An.</label> I come to receiu it for theſe 4. cauſes
<list>
                  <item>1. Firſt, to ſhewe my obedience to my Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, who hath ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded me.</item>
                  <item>2. Secondly, that my inward man might be nouriſhed and ſtrengthened by that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly foode of Chriſts body &amp; blood receiued by faith, as my body is nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by corruptible bread and wine.</item>
                  <item>3. Thirdly, to make open profeſſion of my faith in Chriſt, and loue tovvard my neighboures.</item>
                  <item>4. Laſtly, that by the reuerend miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ioyfull ſhewing foorth of this holy miſterie, my minde, &amp; all the parts
<pb facs="tcp:21345:7"/>of my ſoule, might effectually be ſtirred vp through the inwarde woorking of the holy ſpirit to a more earneſt loue of my God and vnfeined thankfulneſſe to his Maieſtie, freely giuen mee in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> 
               <hi>After what ſort ought you to come to this holy miſtery of the lords ſupper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>An.</label> Three things are cheefly required of thoſe that come to this heauenlye banket of the Lords ſupper.</p>
            <p>The one is a ſorrowfull feeling and a harty lothing of all my ſinne, that is to ſay of all that I haue conceiued in my hart vttered with my tongue, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by outward deedes contrarie to the woorde of God.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is a true faithe in Chriſt, which bringeth with it a comfortable and ioyful feeling of the infinite mercy and euerlaſting looue of God towarde me in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The laſt is a carefull earneſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant endeuor to pleaſe God in al things according to the rule of his woord, and ſo to behaue my ſelfe before him all the dayes of my life as I may beſt profite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and moſt ſet foorth his glory in that calling wherein he hath placed me.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:21345:8"/>
            <head>¶ A forme of prayer to be vſed in <hi>Chriſtian famelies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE thank thee (O Lord God and moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull father) for all thy louing kindnes and vnſpeakeable goodnes ſo aboun dantly declared tovvard vs, in preſeruing vs this daye paſt &amp; all our life hetherto, in turning avvay from vs innu merable plagues vvhich vvee moſt iuſtly haue deſerued, in giuing vnto vs all ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er of bleſſings &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts pertaining vnto this life, &amp; the life to come, and namely vve praiſe &amp; thanke thy mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtie for creating vs according to thine one i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, for ſauing vs from our ſinnes &amp; thy wrath by the merits of thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, for cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs vnto the knovvledge of this thy infinite loue tovvard vs, by the preaching of thy vvord and vvork of thy ſpirit, for ayding and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs ſo fatherlye at all tymes, in all places, &amp; againſt all our enemies vvhich haue ſought by all meanes to turne vs from the earneſt loue of thy Goſpell and obedience of thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. We confeſſe (O Lord) from the bottome of our hartes, that vve are vtterly vnworthy of the leaſt of theſe thy mercies, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be found in vs, to mooue thy maieſty thus bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully to deale with vs, yea that our ma nifold ſins and corruptions of our nature yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in vs, haue deſerud the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. To thee therfore (O father) vve re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der al thanks, al praiſe &amp; glory, for theſe thy benefits beſtovved vpon vs &amp; the reſt of our brethren. And vvc moſt humbly beſech thee, to pardon al our coldnes, vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes vvith al the reſt of our ſins, and to ſtrike our ſtony harts yet more deepely vvith the force of thy ſpirit &amp; edg of thy vvord faithfully preached that we may more earneſtly repent for our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:21345:8"/>iniquities, loathing and abhoring all ſin in our ſelues and others, becauſe it is ſo foule and odious in thine eyes. And we alſo moſt humbly craue at thy hands, more and more to roote out of our harts our owne natural corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, ſelfe loue, pride, enuie, vaine glory, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſnes &amp; all hipocriſy, &amp; to renew in vs dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all thy graces and fruites of thy ſpirit, in that thou in thy wiſedome ſeeſt to be needful for vs, for the better ſetting forrh of thy glory, &amp; more fruitefull ſeruice to our brethren, in thoſe call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings wherein thou haſte placed euery one of vs. Let thy feare (O deare father) be alwaies ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before our eyes, &amp; the moſt comfortable fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thy aboundant loue toward vs in Chriſt, ſo ſtrongly preuaile in our harts, that we neuer preſume to offend thy maieſty by wilfull brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thy lawes, but be found alwaies cherful, dilligent &amp; zealous in all good woorks which thou haſt enioined, &amp; commended vnto vs in thy holy word, Let vs not (O Lord) be like the rude &amp; ignoraunt multitude, who becauſe they haue not knowne thy word, nor effectually taſted of thy loue in heauenly things, are caried with the rage of their owne carnall luſts &amp; worldly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, to al filthines of Idolatry, vncleaneſſe of life, couetous, deceiptfull, &amp; vnrighteous dealing for their owne gaine: But as thou in mercy haſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs from our ſelues &amp; out of this vaine world to ſerue thy Maieſty, to be called and to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede thy chyldren, heires of an immortall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, temples of thy ſpirit &amp; liuely me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, of thy ſonne our ſauiour: ſo graunt that our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, behauiour, &amp; vvhol life may anſvver to this high calling and glory of our profeſsion, a bounding in all ſpiritual knowledge, in feruency
<pb facs="tcp:21345:9"/>of true zeale in deteſtation of all ſinne, in careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to pleaſe thee in all things, ioye of the ſpirit, in peace of conſcience, in all Charitable iuſt and kinde dealing toward all men for thy ſake. And becauſe all our labors in our callings are in vain, without thy meruelous bleſsing, voutchſafe to be alwayes preſent vvith vs, not onely ſhevving vs by the light of thy vvoord vvhat vve ſhould doo, but alſo bleſsing and proſpering vs by the povv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thy ſhielde in all that vve take in hand, in ſuch ſort as ſoome vvoorthy fruite may riſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the comfort of our ovvne conſcience, the benefite of our brethren, and the praiſe of thy holy name through Ieſus Chriſte our Lord. Giue vs thy vviſedome from aboue, vvhereby vve may vſe the things of this vvorld, as though vve vſed them not, trauailing faythfully in our calling, but yet depending of thy prouidence, looking for all good ſucceſſe at thy handes, referring all to thy glory, continually, vvaiting for the comming of our Lord and ſauiour Chriſt Ieſus in vvhoſe name vve pray not onely for our ſelues. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Hugh Singleton</figDesc>
                  <head>HS</head>
                  <q>GOD IS MY HELPER</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21345:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
